Guide to the Ezra Cornell Papers, 1746-1888
Cornell, Ezra Papers, 1746-1888
- Series I. Correspondence 1746-1878
  - Correspondence :: Ezra Cornell Correspondence
    - Correspondence :: Ezra Cornell Correspondence :: 1869-1874
      - June 4, 1870 - August 7, 1870 (Box 33, Folder 13)
        "Since you were here they have got two fine bridges. One over the Chippewa where the Ferry was and the other over the Eau Claire. The town has grown decidedly in the time and the R.R. will add much more to it. This addition of R.R. facilities will add to the value of our lands and increase the sales."
        Saratoga Springs, N.Y.; Eau Claire, Wis.; St. Paul, Minn.
        Emery, F.M.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Gould, John Stanton; White, Andrew Dickson; Fiske, Willard.
      - August 8, 1870 - Letter from Ezra Cornell to Son Frank (Box 100, Folder 4)
      - August 9, 1870 - December 5, 1870 (Box 33, Folder 14)
        Hartt expedition to South America; Cornell University: buildings, University Museum; Sibley Building; Minnesota lands; Albany Agricultural Works.
        August 23, 1870. Andrew Dickson White to Ezra Cornell:
        "The immediate completion of the Sibley Building is of immense importance to us. We are at present utterly crippled in our department of Mechanic Arts for want of just such accomodations as the Sibley Building will give. I insist that this building now is worth two or three buildings later."
        Gould, John Stanton; Hartt, Ch. Fred.; White, Andrew Dickson; Emery, C.F.; McGraw, John; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Cornell, Mary Ann.
      - December 14, 1870 - January 28, 1871 (Box 33, Folder 15)
        Land scrip; Wisconsin lands; Kansas lands; Townsend's Historical Collections; Cornell University: natural history collections; Minnesota lands.
        January 17, 1871. Andrew Dickson White to Ezra Cornell:
        "Keep close watch over our beloved University. Take no more risks than are absolutely necessary. Watch the monthly statements. Insist on knowing just where we are and what we can rely upon. Pardon this reiteration -- it is because I honor you and love our great enterprise. Good bye. God bless you."
        O'Reilly, Henry; White, Andrew Dickson; Cornell, A.B.
      - January 30, 1871 - April 29, 1871 (Box 33, Folder 16)
        Albany Agricultural Works.
        Emery, W.S.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Emery, Horace L.
      - May 1, 1871 - August 12, 1871 (Box 34, Folder 1)
        Cornell University: rowing (Cornell Navy); Genealogical Register; Wisconsin lands; women's education.
        Hughes, Thomas; Sage, H.W.; Woodward, W.A.; Chester, E.W.; Cornell, D.B.; Eastman, Emma; White, Andrew Dickson.
      - August 15, 1871 - November 21, 1871 (Box 34, Folder 2)
        Cornell villa; Wisconsin lands; Minnesota lands; Cornell University; National Telegraph Memorial Monument; Land Grant Act.
        Sage, H.W.; Knight, John H.
      - November 22, 1871 - December 23, 1871 (Box 34, Folder 3)
        Cornell University: buildings, plan; Land Grant Act; Wisconsin lands.
        December 13, 1871. Andrew Dickson White to Ezra Cornell:
        "Finch tells me that you have the draft of a bill looking to the ratification of your contract with this State by Congress. I wish you would hold on a little about that until we can confer upon it.
        "Sage is probably to be here tomorrow. He aches to begin his College, evidently."
        Sage, H.W.; White, Andrew Dickson.
      - January 2, 1872 - February 10, 1872 (Box 34, Folder 4)
        Cornell University: Library, equipment and supplies, Sage College; Sparks collections of books and manuscripts; Benjamin Franklin papers; photo-lithography business; Land Grant Act.
        North Carolina.
        Fiske, Willard; Wood, M.B; White, Andrew Dickson; Cornell, W.S.
      - February 12, 1872 - March 12, 1872 (Box 34, Folder 5)
        Cornell University: Library, equipment and supplies, Sage College, rowing (Cornell Navy); Land Grant Act.
        Woodward, W.A.; Cornell, W.S.; Stanton, Elizabeth Cady; Cornell, Mary Ann; White, Andrew Dickson; Brown, Mary; Sage, H.W.
      - March 13, 1872 - April 25, 1872 (Box 34, Folder 6)
        Cornell University: buildings, presidency; Wisconsin lands.
        April 2, 1872. Andrew Dickson White to Ezra Cornell regarding the sale of college lands, a contemplated resignation of the Presidency, the building of a private residence, and the long-range development of the University.
        Chester, E.W.; White, Andrew Dickson.
      - May 1, 1872 - August 16, 1872 (Box 34, Folder 7)
        Albany Agricultural Works; Cornell University: trustees, Sage College.
        Emery, Horace L.; White, Andrew Dickson; Folger, Charles J.; Babcock, Charles.
      - August 21, 1872 - October 3, 1872 (Box 34, Folder 8)
        Cornell University: Department of Architecture, professors, Sage College, Sage Chapel, trustees, College of Chemistry and Physics; telegraph industry; Cascadilla Place; Albany Agricultural Works; Wisconsin lands; Cooper Institute.
        Babcock, Charles; White, Andrew Dickson; Emery, Horace L.; Sage, H.W.
      - October 7, 1872 - December 6, 1872 (Box 34, Folder 9)
        Cornell University; Wisconsin lands; Albany Agricultural Works.
        November 20, 1872. Ezra Cornell to John Horn recalling the early development of the telegraph.
        Cornell, W.M.; Sage, H.W.; White, Andrew Dickson; Hunt, T.S.; Horn, John.
      - December 7, 1872 - January 31, 1873 (Box 34, Folder 10)
        Cornell University: Library, professors; Wisconsin lands; Minnesota lands; Morrill Bill; Albany Agricultural Works; National Telegraph Memorial Monument.
        Sage, H.W.; Morrill, Justin S.; Gregory, J.M.; White, Andrew Dickson; Russel, William C.
      - February 4, 1873 - March 19, 1873 (Box 34, Folder 11)
        Cornell University: Library,; Agriculture,; Agricultural College Bill,; entomology collections,; Geneva and Ithaca Railroad Co.,; Land script
        February 16, 1873. Ezra Cornell to Hon. Nelson K. Hopkins regarding withdraw of 1025 shares of Western Union stock in accordance with contract of November 1865 and development of the University.
        Also a February 19, 1873 letter from A. D. White discussing Cornell's copy of Piranesi.
        White, Andrew Dickson; Gould, John Stanton; Fiske, Willard; Hartt, Ch. Fred.; Wilder, Burt Green; Hopkins, Nelson K.; Comstock, John.
      - March 22, 1873 - May 27, 1873 (Box 34, Folder 12)
        Cornell University: faculty, Geology Department; Cornell villa; Albany Agricultural Works; Land Grant Act; German-American Society; calumniation of Ezra Cornell by Mr. McGuire in the New York State Legislature regarding financial arrangement of western lands and the founding and endowment of the University.
        White, Andrew Dickson; Hartt, Ch. Fred.; Emery, Horace L.; Dix, John A.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Austin, George L.
      - May 28, 1873 - June 29, 1873 (Box 34, Folder 13)
        Calumniation of Ezra Cornell by Mr. McGuire in the New York State Legislature regarding financial arrangement of western lands and the founding and endowment of the University; mineralogical collections; Cornell University; Western Union Telegraph Company: stock.
        Blair, Charles Hildreth; Seymour, Horatio; Cornell, W.J.; White, Andrew Dickson; Wood, M.B.; Parker, Amasa J.; Austin, George L.
      - June 30, 1873 - August 1, 1873 (Box 34, Folder 14)
        Wisconsin lands; Albany Agricultural Works; Cornell University: faculty.
        Coffin, Isaac N.; Morse, Samuel F.B.; Emery, Horace L.; Rooker, Thomas N.; White, Andrew Dickson.
      - August 2, 1873 - September 21, 1873 (Box 34, Folder 15)
        Also an undigitized letter to Hon. N. K. Hopkins, Comptroller, Sept. 16, 1873 re stocks, including Western Union. There is more conversation regarding Hopkins and stocks in October.
        Cornell University: faculty, salaries, Agricultural Department; New York State Legislature; Wisconsin lands; Albany Agricultural Works.
        Hartt, Ch. Fred.; McCandless, H.; White, Andrew Dickson; Cleaves, E.C.
      - October 6, 1873 - January 28, 1874 (Box 34, Folder 16)
        Geneva and Ithaca Railroad Company.
        McGraw, John; Greenough, J.; White, Andrew Dickson.
      - February 1, 1874 - May 26, 1874 (Box 34, Folder 17)
        Cornell University: Sage College, Agricultural Department; calumniation of Ezra Cornell by Mr. McGuire in the New York State Legislature regarding financial arrangement of western lands and the founding and endowment of the University; Ithaca Iron Company; Geneva and Ithaca Railroad Company; railroads; Albany Agricultural Works; telegraph industry; women's education; cattle.
        April 13, 1874. Ezra Cornell to Edward Clasbeck:
        "It is 30 years this month since I purchased the poles for the line between Washington & Baltimore upon which the first wires were suspended, very few had faith in the success of the enterprise at that time, Prof. Morse('s) failure to make the wires work through leaden pipes beneath the surface of the earth had shaken his faith, but the wires were on the poles by 1st May 1844, and the line got to work with remarkable success considering the clumsy instruments we had to work with. Great changes have taken place since that time, but few of us who contributed to the success of the Telegraph remain to witness the fact that it has become the most important agency in the affairs of mankind - and with those few I desire a reunion."
        April 15, 1874. Ezra Cornell to John Horn describing the development of the telegraph:
        "The suggestion for putting the wires on poles came to Prof. Morse and myself about the same time from reading the reports in an English work of the necessity Prof. Wheatstone found for putting his wires on poles after a failure in pipes similar to that of Prof. Morse."
        Finch, F.M.; Burt, William L.; Greenough, J.; McChain, George; Clasbeck, Edward; Parker, Amasa J.; Roberts, Isaac P.
      - May 27, 1874 - August 15, 1874 (Box 34, Folder 18)
        Cattle; Utica, Ithaca and Elmira Railroad; Sodus Point and Southern Rail Road Company.
        Rooker, Thomas N.; Sherwood, Thomas D.
      - August 26, 1874 - October 17, 1874 (Box 34, Folder 19)
        Cornell University; cattle; life insurance.
        Robinson, Orrin; White, Andrew Dickson; Emery, H. Herbert.
      - October 21, 1874 - December 13, 1874 (Box 34, Folder 20)
        Cornell villa; Albany Agricultural Works; life insurance.
        Cornell, D.B.
    - Correspondence :: Ezra Cornell Correspondence :: Undated Correspondence of Ezra Cornell
      Telegraph industry; family news from Michigan; Cornell University; appeal to Ezra Cornell for aid.
      Undated letters of Emory Cobb, Henry O'Reilly, J.J. Speed, J.H. Wade, Theodore Faxton, E.W. Chester, Phebe Wood, Henry Wells, Wesley Newcomb, Goldwin Smith, Horace L. Emery, Jeremiah Beebe, Alonzo B. Cornell, Thomas N. Rooker, and others; includes letters from individuals who do not occur elsewhere in the Cornell Papers.
      This undated material pertains to the telegraph industry, the Wood family in Albion Michigan, Cornell University, and includes several appeals to Ezra Cornell for aid.
      Many pieces are fragments, scraps, or parts of dated letters; the undated correspondence includes calling cards, and drafts of outgoing letters by Ezra Cornell concerning several important matters of the telegraph industry, the Cornell family, and the University.
      Cobb, Emory; O'Reilly, Henry; Speed, J.J.; Wade, J.H.; Faxton, Theodore; Chester, E.W.; Wood, Phebe; Wells, Henry; Newcomb, Wesley; Smith, Goldwin; Emery, Horace L.; Beebe, Jeremiah; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Rooker, Thomas N.
      - [Untitled] (Box 35, Folder 1)
      - [Untitled] (Box 35, Folder 2)
      - [Untitled] (Box 35, Folder 3)
      - [Untitled] (Box 35, Folder 4)
      - [Untitled] (Box 35, Folder 5)
      - [Untitled] (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - Photostats of correspondence (1843-1856) (Box 98)
    - Photostats of correspondence (1857-1874) (Box 99)
  - Correspondence :: Cornell Family Correspondence
    - [November 13, 1746] July 2, 1778 - May 17, 1819 (Box 36, Folder 1)
      Cornell family correspondence: letters to Elijah and Eunice Cornell from relatives with notices of births and deaths and local news.
      DeRuyter; Westchester County, N.Y.; North Carolina.
      Cornell, Elijah; Cornell, Eunice; Barnard, Elizabeth; Macy, Anna; Cornell, Ezra (brother of Elijah); Chace, Phebe.
    - August 19, 1820 - August 5, 1838 (Box 36, Folder 2)
      Cornell family correspondence: letters to Elijah and Eunice Cornell in DeRuyter from their children and other relatives; notices of births and deaths, requests for permission to marry, local news, reports on family health, and mention of women's work.
      August 13, 1837. Martin B. Wood to Elijah Cornell:
      "As a matter consequent upon human life I have for a course of years studiously regarded the motions and movements of my female acquaintance for the purpose of discovering one among the multitude who possessed the requisite qualities for rendering the married life preferable to any other and of the number of ladies that have fallen within the circle of my acquaintance I feel it my imperitive duty to bestow upon your daughter Phebe, the preferance."
      DeRuyter; Ithaca; Providence; Rochester; North Carolina.
      Cornell, Elijah; Cornell, Eunice; Cornell, E.B.; Cornell, Lucretia; Cornell, Benjamin; Cornell, Mary; Cornell, Phebe; Cornell, Paul; Earle, Rhoda; Macy, Anna; Chace, Thomas; Wood, M. B.
    - September 15, 1838 - February 4, 1844 (Box 36, Folder 3)
      Cornell family correspondence: letters to Elijah and Eunice Cornell in DeRuyter from their children and other relatives; letters to Mary Ann Cornell; news of births, deaths, illnesses, local events, and messages of sympathy.
      DeRuyter; Ithaca; Fall River; Providence; Seneca Falls.
      Cornell, Elijah; Cornell, Eunice; Cornell, Mary; Cornell, E.B.; Wood, Phebe; Chace, Lucretia; Chace, Thomas; Chace, Palmer; Macy, Anna; Macy, Robert; Bristol, John S.; Bristol, Elmira; Cornell, Mary Ann.
    - February 10, 1844 - August 20, 1845 (Box 36, Folder 4)
      Cornell family correspondence: letters to Elijah and Eunice Cornell in Ithaca from their children concerning travel and new homes in Michigan; letters from Thomas Chace telling of Lucretia's illness and death; correspondence among Ezra Cornell's siblings; news of family life, travel, health, deaths, and local events.
      Michigan; Providence; DeRuyter; Washington, D.C.
      Cornell, Elijah; Cornell, Eunice; Cornell, Mary; Wood, Phebe; Cornell, E.S.; Cornell, Deborah; Chace, Lucretia; Chace, Thomas; Cornell, Mary Ann; Wood, O.S.; Wood, Deborah C.; Cornell, E.B.; Bristol, Elmira.
    - August 25, 1845 - March 8, 1847 (Box 36, Folder 5)
      Cornell family correspondence: letters to Elijah and Eunice Cornell in Ithaca from their children in Michigan and from cousin Elizabeth Swain in Nantucket; correspondence between Cornell and Wood siblings; news of family life, health, illnesses, business, children, travel, and religion.
      Ithaca; Albion; Homer, Mich.; Nantucket.
      Cornell, Elijah; Cornell, Eunice; Robertson, Mary C.; Robertson, Hiram D.; Cornell, E.S.; Wood, Phebe; Wood, M.B.; Chace, Thomas; Swain, Elizabeth; Cornell, Mary Ann; Wood, O.S.; Bristol, Elmira; Cornell, John H.
    - March 13, 1847 - October 10, 1848 (Box 36, Folder 6)
      Cornell family correspondence: letters to Elijah and Eunice Cornell from their children in Michigan and New York with news of religious conversions, children, illnesses, pottery, and family life; letters to Mary Ann Cornell from E.B. and Betsy Ann Cornell; letter to John Cornell from Elijah concerning Mary Ann and Ezra Cornell's trip to Michigan; M.B. Wood to Phebe Wood while he is away from home building telegraph lines.
      Union Springs, N.Y.; Homer; Albion; Nantucket.
      Cornell, Alonzo B.; Cornell, Elijah; Cornell, Eunice; Cornell, E.S.; Cornell, D.B.; Cornell, John H.; Cornell, E.B.; Cornell, Betsy Ann; Cornell, Mary Ann; Chace, Thomas; Robertson, Mary C.; Wood, M.B.; Wood, Phebe.
    - March 23, 1847 - Letter to Ezra Cornell from Cousin Ann Eliza Lacy (Box 100, Folder 2)
    - November 5, 1848 - March 3, 1850 (Box 36, Folder 7)
      Cornell family correspondence: letters to Elijah and Eunice Cornell in Ithaca from their children; letters among siblings and aunts and nieces; letters to Mary Ann; news of family events, life in Albion, health, school, social life, and growth of children; gold fever; pottery business; Phebe as telegraph operator.
      January 14, 1849. Jane Cornell to Mary Ann Cornell:
      "I suppose that Father thinks about starting for California in search of Gold, tell him not to do so untill Spring and I will go with him. Mart is very strongly attracted with the Feaver but has not started for there yet?. The people of Albion hold California meetings here two or three times a week, and there is a large company going from here early in the Spring. Do you know where Daniel is at present. I should not wonder if he was in California by this time."
      Albion; Union Springs; Fall River, Mass.
      Cornell, Elijah; Cornell, Eunice; Cornell, John H.; Robertson, Mary C.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Dunham, J.; Cornell, Elizabeth P.; Cornell, Jane; Cornell, D.B.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Wood, Deborah C.; Wood, Phebe; Chace, Palmer.
    - March 5, 1850 - August 29, 1852 (Box 36, Folder 8)
      Cornell family correspondence: letters to Elijah and Eunice Cornell from their children and from siblings in Fall River, Massachusetts; correspondence among Ezra Cornell's siblings; many letters from D.B. Cornell to parents and siblings; news of family life, religion, and schooling.
      DeRuyter; Albion; Union Springs; Providence; Canada; Fall River; Ithaca.
      Cornell, Elijah; Cornell, Eunice; Robertson, Mary C.; Cornell, D.B.; Chace, Thomas; Cornell, Jane; Cornell, John H.; Wood, Phebe; Chace, Miller; Cornell, E.B.; Shepard, S.E.; Chace, Mary.
    - September 1, 1852 - December 27, 1857 (Box 36, Folder 9)
      Cornell family correspondence: letters to Elijah and Eunice Cornell from their children and grandchildren; correspondence among Ezra Cornell's siblings; news of health, employment, farming, and life in Michigan.
      Albion; Union Springs; Fall River; Brantford, Ontario; Ithaca; Providence; Pine River, Mich.
      Cornell, Jane; Cornell, D.B.; Wood, Phebe; Chace, Miller; Cornell, Molly; Cornell, E.S.; Cornell, Elijah; Cornell, Eunice; Cornell, E.B.; Chace, Rebecca; Cornell, Mary Ann; Cornell, John H.; Wood, Deborah C.
    - December 28, 1857 - February 10, 1860 (Box 36, Folder 10)
      Cornell family correspondence: letters to Elijah from his children, grandchildren, and brother; correspondence among Ezra Cornell's siblings; selection of Mary Ann Cornell as Judge of Needlework at the State Fair; news of deaths, women's fashions, family life, health, homes, and crops.
      Pine River; Albion; Fall River; Belvidere, Ill.; Brantford; Iowa; Albany.
      Cornell, Elijah; Cornell, E.S.; Wood, Phebe; Robertson, Hiram D.; Robertson, Mary C.; Cornell, John H.; Rowell, Mary; Cornell, Mary Ann; Cornell, D.B.; Cornell, Molly; Cornell, Jane; Chase, Edward; Chace, Alonzo; Chace, Miller.
    - March 1, 1860 - January 3, 1863 (Box 36, Folder 11)
      Cornell family correspondence: letters to Elijah from his children, grandchildren, and brother; letters to Mary Ann from O.H. Perry at Agricultural College in Ovid; letters between Frank and Mary Ann; news of life in Ithaca, family life, O.H. Perry's marriage, new babies.
      July 7, 1860. E.B. Cornell to Elijah Cornell from Ithaca discussing local news and family news, including a 'baloon assension' in Ithaca and the work he is doing for Ezra Cornell.
      December 15, 1860. Benjamin Cornell to Elijah Cornell from Agricultural College in Ovid:
      "I'm well at present & going to College at Ovid with Perry?. The College to where we go is intended to give a student a good thorough education in English languages & cemistry & also other branches to numerous to mention. With a practical knowledge of Agriculture. The College is large enough to accomodate 200 students. They have a farm attached to it of 600 acres to practice & experiment on."
      December 18, 1860. O.H. Perry Cornell to Mary Ann Cornell from Agricultural College at Ovid:
      "I received your letter this evening and was very glad to hear from you on account of the carpet for I tell you this room is enough to make the strongest man in the State of New York homesick?"
      June 4, 1861. Edward S. Cornell to Elijah from Michigan Asylum discussing his health, the Asylum, and his desire to return to his farm.
      Albion; Ohio; Fall River; Ithaca; Ovid, N.Y.
      Robertson, Mary C.; Wood, Phebe; Chace, Miller; Cornell, E.B.; Cornell, Benjamin; Cornell, O.H. Perry; Cornell, E.S.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Cornell, Franklin C.
    - January 11, 1863 - December 8, 1874 (Box 36, Folder 12)
      Cornell family correspondence: letters to Mary Ann Cornell from family (children, siblings, and cousins) and friends; news of family life, health, deaths, Ithaca, and grandchildren; letter of thanks from Dr. C.S. Lozier for Cornell Scholarship; Cornell family genealogy and history; Cornell family English legacy; M.B. Wood to Phebe Wood describing his trip to Washington, D.C.
      December 8, 1874. Mary Ann Cornell to E.B. Cornell:
      "Ezra received your letter of the 6th this morning and requested me to answer it as he is unable to write?he is very feble indeed but we hope he will get about again soon, he has about finished the business of settleing with the University and that is a great load off his mind. I hope he will get his matters in shape so he can give more attention to geting his health restored and less to business, the boys are all doing all they can to assist him, and I hope it will all come out right."
      Albion; DeRuyter; Ithaca; Washington, D.C.
      Cornell, Mary Ann; Dunham, Emily; Dunham, J.; Wood, Phebe; Barnard, Eunice; Lozier, C.S.; Cornell, Sue; Cornell, Franklin C.; Cornell, Betsy Ann; Chace, Anna; Allen, Clara; Cornell, D.B.; Wood, M.B.; Cornell, E.B.
    - December 13, 1874 - September 5, 1878 (Box 36, Folder 13)
      Cornell family correspondence: letter of sympathy to Mary Ann Cornell; correspondence among Ezra Cornell's siblings concerning his death and family news.
      January 24, 1875. D.B. Cornell to J.H. Cornell from Colorado:
      "Yours of 16th recieved this morning, in which you say that Brother Ezra was very much embarassed during the last year of his life & you express the fear that there will not be much left &c. I am not surprised at the information as E had wrote to me in the summer that if his R.R. project failed I would probably be better off than he would be. I was however in hopes that he would make a success of that as he had intimated to me that he should, if successful in that, then quit active business & seek the rest he so much needed & desired?
      "I have had trouble with my wife more or less ever since we were married & I expect she will soon leave me. I am well assured that she expected Ezra would make a will & leave her some money independant from me & now that she has failed on that I think she will leave soon."
      Also discussion of opportunities in Colorado.
      Colorado; Albion.
      Cornell, D.B.; Robertson, Mary C.; Cornell, John H.; Cornell, Franklin C.; Wood, M.B.; Cornell, E.S.
    - Undated Correspondence of the Cornell Family (Box 36, Folder 14)
      Cornell family correspondence: letters to Elijah and Eunice Cornell from their children; news of family life, children, health, fashions, farming, and employment.
      n.d. Mary Cornell to Eunice Cornell: